[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio is brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine online at computer org
slash software for software engineering
radio this is Robert bloomin today I'm
joined by Monica Beckwith Monica is an
independent consultant specializing in
optimizing the java virtual machine and
garbage collection for enterprise
applications she's a regular speaker at
conferences and has published articles
on topics including garbage collection
the Java memory model and others Marco
is the performance lead on the g1
garbage collector and named a Java 1
2013 rockstar monica welcome to software
engineering radio thank you there
anything else about yourself you'd like
the listeners to know yeah I think that
you summed it up pretty well I've been
working as a performance engineer Java
performance engineer for more than a
decade I used to work for Advanced Micro
Devices and that's how I kind of got
into the JVM GC JIT compiler alone and I
worked primarily with hotspot which is
like the open JDK hotspot garbage
collector and the compiler the JVM
itself but I also briefly worked with
Jim rocket and IBM's channel so yeah it
goes along but you know I started with a
you know just optimizing and rush using
the right stick right instructions
optimizing that generated code
eventually moved on to trying to
optimize the compiler the JIT compiler
itself and then finally moved on do
garbage collector and then that's where
I stayed I kind of work with the garbage
for that mostly server-side garbage
collection so like the throughput
collector the work with CMS that I'm
going mostly conjoined mark-and-sweep
and then finally qi1 GC and that's where
been working with g10
I'm really looking forward to your
insights on garbage collection which is
the topic of our show like to start out
with some basic background starting with
the question what is garbage garbage in
simple terms is something that you don't
need anymore that is not referenced
anymore when you look at it for example
in Java when you look at the Java heap
objects are allocated on the heap and
most often that they're not you can
think of it as a sort of a linked list
so you have to read set and then
whatever is reference from the root set
is is life right and then you need to
mark it and so and so forth but what is
not referenced it's still occupying
space in the heat so that needs to be
collected so to speak or sweet you know
so that the unreferenced
object which is not referenced by
anything on your heap and your any other
object on the heap and it doesn't
directly connect to the root indirectly
or directly connect to the root set then
that can be reclaimed and that is known
as knowledge you describe a basic
garbage collection algorithm that would
be common to any language that has
garbage collection sure so garbage
collection let's start from what garbage
collection means it's not just the
collection itself but it's also the
allocation so for example in Java when
when you allocate when your application
allocates an object it gets a carbon to
garbage collector handles the allocation
and then there is the fast path
allocation usually which is optimized to
to not have synchronization overhead
then there comes the collection part
where when when the objects are not
reachable they need to be sweet they
need to be collected so so what happens
is that the heap is a finite amount of
memory and 1 1 so if you if you talk
about generational heat for example when
the young generation or the old
generation gets full and you cannot
allocate anymore or do not promote
anymore
that's one in the garbage collector
kicks in for for the garbage collector
to start at a particular point and kind
of make an object graph with the object
tree you know those trees need to have
one or more projects right so what I
mean by these you talk we'd set
basically like local variable that's
right and then so and then your Java
threads themselves you know if you have
the active Java threads then then those
are your GC roots there's one agency
that's there's also the J&I references
static marigolds at all plants so you
start from that set and anything that's
any object tree that's reachable from
the read set is considered live and
that's what is called as marking so
you're marking on the live objects so
once all the live objects are marked
what's remaining are the ones that are
not reachable you know when you're when
you're doing this object graph and so
those those don't seem to be seem to fit
into after crap so those are considered
garbage and then you have different
algorithms to to to take care of the
garbage
okay so there's most most commonly known
as sleeping and then sweeping is also
optimized you don't have to go through
the entire heap to sweep to collect
these garbage you can have for example
what CMS does has a free list so as as
and when it goes through you know when
it's doing this sweeping in these these
garbage spaces are maintained in a free
list so you don't have to sit down go
through their childhood so there are
different optimizations that you can do
but most common algorithm you would find
that everybody every bunch collector has
to mark and then has to take care of
cleaning out you know and the way it
cleans up is could be scavenging and all
those things that different algorithms
that you could go ahead and optimize and
I think the one the hotspot garbage
collector
most common ones are the young
generation is a copying compacting
collector and the old generation leave
the fail the failsafe is Mark Smith
compound and if and then there is the
CMS which is mostly confluent mark-sweep
there's no compaction there is sheet
wine which is also which does
incremental compaction you talked about
hot spot CMS there these are different
garbage collectors in Java Java has been
a garbage collected language since the
beginning but it has changed its
approach considerably tell us about the
history of garbage collection within the
Java language and what sort of goals or
what has been driving the changes in
garbage collection well you you you were
right on target Java always has had
automatic management memory management
so because that takes care of allocating
and deallocating saying you don't have
to do it and like you would have to
would have to do in a programming
language Lexy and and that way the whole
purpose was that was that you users
don't have to take care of it because in
C we have a lot of problem if you do not
D allocate you know you keep on using up
memory and your not forget to deallocate
or whatever happens no Java takes care
of it and one of the reasons is that
it's heat based right so we have a limit
to a finite amount of heat and which you
can set with your ma you know maximum
XML action X M s and X and X options so
initial and maximum heat sizes and so at
first it was I mean it's always been a
simple algorithm that I said mark sweet
and compact or whatever so in in job and
hot spot GC who started with something
called the serial GC very simple single
single threaded collection right so the
only it pauses the application threads
does its collection just using single
garbage collection read so that way
the data structures are very simple
minimal footprint and and that was
working great and then we figured out
that the heaps are growing the server
demands it during their multi cores that
have come in Java has always been a
multi-threaded application you know
language programming languages so so now
we wanted to make sure that the garbage
collector is going with the needs of the
market right so then in comes this
stupid collector but before even the
trooper collection they was we were
hitting a bottleneck but with that
single generation so every time it had
to pause it it paused and collected the
entire heap to mark them very productive
that jang-hee that was not working
because now you have this humongous
pause and only you know and then you
connected so if your heap is growing so
you have to mark and sweep the entire
heap this this huge heap so then in
comes this generational collector so the
principle of a generation collector is
that most objects daeyoung
which is which makes perfect sense
because a heap doesn't have similarly
aged or aging objects or what happens is
that when you're allocating you may be
creating more garbage within the first
you know the first few seconds of your
allocation and then at the same time
you're building up this cache or
building up this what we call is my data
set while you're also doing other
allocations that may not eventually end
up in your life data set so the
generation principle is that you
allocate these young objects in
something something called a young
generation and then you agent and the
way you age them is that you move them
back and forth in the survivor space and
then once you have aged them
appropriately you promote them into the
old generation so now hopefully the the
goal is that the old generation has what
we call a live data set so your long
object not medium lived but long live
objects get promoted that's the whole
goal of this generation of generational
collection right so what you're talking
about generational then is there might
be some global objects that I load from
a database of config file that I load
right at the beginning and they're gonna
be there for the entire duration of the
program runtime whereas inside a little
function I need a string and it gets
allocated and I almost immediately don't
need us you're trying to optimize
different garbage collection strategies
based on these very trenchant objects
and more like a permanent object is that
is that where you're going yes so for
example like you said something that you
allocate like a string and they don't
need it that kind of if if for example
you had put it in the old generation if
we for some reason we didn't age it
appropriately and immediately promote it
into the old generation now what happens
is when it dies it creates this hole in
the old generation and but it's still
it's still there even though it's
garbage it's still there and it's
occupying this space that could have
been used for your long-lived objects so
eventually if you have more of these
short-lived objects that will have
stayed up stating your own generation
your generation is full of garbage and
now need you need to kick in an old
generation collection all generation
collections are usually more expensive
because it can all generation usually is
a bigger part bigger chunk of your heap
so you want to do the or transient ones
more frequently lower-cost more
aggressive collection if you can sort
things into the old generation they may
not change and you may not have to
garbage collect those very often that's
the goal especially with something like
this penguin mark and sweet collection
what happens there is that old
generation collection is mostly
concurrent and at the same time it's not
compacted so if we promote if you
prematurely promote your objects you
have and then clinton market sweet kicks
in it just sweeps it so you have in
space de-allocation
and then of course you have this free
list which panicky
track of all these D allocated spaces
that when the new objects are promoted
even if they have to fit in these chunks
of free space so sometimes they may not
be able to fit in the chunks of free
space and eventually you could run out
of heat all generation space and
unfortunately even though you had so if
you think of it not your entire all
generation is not not live objects
they're garbage there's it's chunks but
unfortunately since you cannot fit in
your promoted objects of those chunks
you are expect experiencing
fragmentation a sense of fragmentations
work you might have enough free memory
if you added it all up yes there isn't a
single slot that is large enough for the
allocation that you need to do that is
correct that is correct and that's a big
problem but confirm mark-and-sweep
so to handle that what happens is the
failsafe to fall back mark sweet compact
GC which is also called the full GC and
kicks in and then it channels the entire
heap and it's single threaded just like
in the serial GC so it's a long slow
process so what people have end up doing
to avoid that they have you know at the
end of their day you know they they kick
in the flow GC and throughout the day
they just deal with young young
generation collections and sweeping
which is really fast so there are lots
of ports around it yeah so you did
mention compacting that is I understand
it's like when I run disk defrag on my
computer but it's on the working memory
and the heap is that right
so compaction is in Kendall different
ways and different generations but the
way it's handled in young generation
it's done by copying so so if you think
of young general if you draw up this
kind of semi spaces one is called what's
called leftmost one Eden and then we'll
call the rightmost one as survivors
within survivors you can have s0 and s1
not not with
g 1g c but in the food essences you had
s uranus what would you survive g1 is
another one of the java garbage
collector yes and g one just has eaten
an survivor space the other garbage
collector is not even from space and to
space survivors or you could call them s
0 and s 1 survivors so let's just so
when allocations happen into the Eden
after the Eden gets full this young
collection is triggered so when the
young collection is triggered all the
live objects are copied to these
survivors phases and in in prior to g1
they copied in say s 0 from space so
when the next election happens which
means the next time the Eden gets full
Eden plus s 0 are live objects in Eden
plus s 0 are copied into s 1 so this
copying back and forth of from s 0 to s
1 of surviving objects is called is
called copying compassion that achieves
compassion by itself because after every
collection Eden is completely empty
right okay so when you copy
you've got from space you've got little
chunks in between the memory and use so
you and you copy you copy everything
contiguous correct yes you can't be
everything one but it you know there is
concept e labs and promotion lands that
I'm not talking about here so that's
that's a whole thing so when you're
promoting for example the garbage
collection threads will from promote
into their promotion labs which is local
area buffers so so that were so there
could be some kind of non-contiguous
depending on which thread gets to what
object person there's like a
work-stealing and all those things that
goes around and catalog when you Federal
Transit employed it so it's similar to
you know whatever optimization you would
do if you had multiple threads right you
would have a work queue you have what
happens to you like you talked about
these evolutionary garbage collection
driven by
need for Java to keep up with market
demands one of the most crucial features
of modern computing is a large number of
cores and memory I can get an instance
on AWS cloud with over 200 gigs of
memory do the modern Java collectors
scale up well across many cores and
large memory yeah and that's a good
question so that this is one of the
reasons why garbage first garbage
collector was introduced so like I
mentioned for CMS and for stupid
collector we have these two generations
there are contiguous young generation
and own generation and as the heat grows
as the number of life objects are
increased you know is the reason you
would have the reason you need more heat
is because you you're trying to increase
your life dataset that's the hope right
I mean also some people increase the
heat because they want to avoid a full
collection as well you know generation
compacting collection as well so did I
understand earlier you said you might
deliberately run like gasm operational
step that a person or a batch job does
the full collection at certain times a
day when either you've taken that know
offline or it's a little okay yes and
people do that all the time yes so back
to the so so there are lots of reasons
why people may want to increase that
their their heap so let's let's assume
that you have one of the reasons that
you're doing it is because you have
increasing the amount of life data said
that you want to fit in your own
generation and you want to have a
collector that is also guaranteeing
certain max response time so garbage
collector that guarantee doesn't
guarantee but you want to keep the pause
low because they're right now in hotspot
there is nothing that as a hard cost I'm
guaranteeing so to speak but but there
is a collectible garbage first garbage
collector which is soft a real-time
guarantee so it it tries to do its best
to match your pass time requirement it
doesn't mean that it it stops the pause
right at your turn
it but it'll try to be try to adjust its
generations and regions so that it can
achieve that target now another good
point of why people may move to garbage
for Irish first garbage collector
especially when they have larger heaps
this is because of the incremental
compaction I briefly mentioned that it's
not it's called mix GC so what happens
is G 1 heap is divided into regions and
the deepest contiguous and the
generations don't have to be contiguous
which means that at a particular time
any region could be a region out of the
young generation or it could be a region
out of the old generation so so when we
have to so there's n there's a threshold
similar to concurrent mark-and-sweep
collector there's a threshold marking
threshold in g1 as well
once these the old generation gets
filled to your threshold you start the
marking cycle so the marking cycle will
go ahead and mark a similar thing right
so going mark and find out the live
object crash now
and it also there's something called the
GC efficiency it also arranges it also
ranges based on the liveness per region
so if the region has to is too expensive
it's too popular so that means
remembered sets are expensive or and too
many live objects in there that region
will not be collected it's it's deemed
too expensive so mostly garbage first
right you know whatever it has more
garbage will be collected that's the
principle of garbage first
so when after the marking completes
there's something called a mix chassis
which has all the young regions and a
few candidate regions from the old
generation so own regions and and it
does the sentimentally it doesn't come
at the entire old generation but it does
so us you know in steps of maybe using
for mixed elections or jh8 mixed
elections after the marking so
that way if you had a 400 kid keep like
you mentioned or 300 K be pleasant you
your you're not collecting the entire
say and the old generation will say 200
kids or whatever right you're not
collecting too entire 200 gigs at a time
you are collecting it incrementally so
that that is a big step for hotspot
because previously the previous garbage
collections may have had a you know they
have a sweet spot which is definitely
way way less then 200 kids right so I
wanted to talk about pauses well let's
start you mentioned pauses explain what
a pause is in garbage collection and
what and why why is there a pause okay
so for hotspot garbage collectors
there's always going to be snapping what
causes okay and the reason they it needs
for hotspot that it needs to be is that
you have the application plans have to
come to a safe point where they can park
themselves and the garbage collector
goes up and Kings okay our moon is up to
two lon right because you because who's
the like I mentioned about the caffeine
collector it's moving from one space to
the other so the objects are the live
objects are moved around same goes with
compaction your moving objects with live
objects so right so you don't want to
move memory while the program is running
begins you might mess something up
pretty badly and and you know some in g1
there's fun for marking and and there's
a the marking algorithm also has
barriers when something rights to it
while look it's Kentucky marking so
there are barriers you can use barriers
to do that as well to do some part of it
in in hotspot for example and the
remainder at any given time once you
have gotten gone through your marketing
and and identified the objects that are
live the hotspot brings the application
threads to a safe point and then it does
the actual moving in and
that's how it does it so to speak
collection the garbage collection now
when the application threads are brought
to a save point that's that's what it is
called as a plus because your
application has passed for the garbage
collector to do its job and that point
is basically dependent on the copying
costs like the moving cost so more like
objects that you have to copy that's how
much time that pause is going to take
right at least it should there could be
other issues right but the majority of
the time that you're spending pausing is
should should be your copying time and
you are removing time which which isn't
in hotspot it stopped in time so I guess
that's what is a pause back when the web
started people were putting up with five
to ten second page load times so you had
a 500 millisecond garbage collection
pause it didn't really impact
application behavior but networks have
gotten a lot faster applications
JavaScript so you don't need to load
your entire page user expectations for
how responsive they want application to
be have really grown and what is the
impact of pauses on responsiveness of
applications and on user experience well
you know to proceed so user experience
and application responsiveness can be
two different things where the user may
not see your garbage collection pause of
hundred milliseconds unusual may not
using may not be able to notice that if
it's just ever once so it's the
frequency of the pauses world right if
the hundred milliseconds are
back-to-back of course you cannot notice
it but if the hundred milliseconds are
ever so often maybe one second or so the
user may not notice it and because
network Dickinson's to be even more net
mention you know it could be more
consuming than that so now how does it
how does it affect the responsiveness of
the application yeah
like again it's the frequency and the
and because duration itself and
eventually this latencies affect the
throughput if you if you think about it
you know how often you pause and how how
much you pants will determine the true
part of your application so Cupid is
basically garbage collection for garbage
collection the truth food is basically
the time that the applications the time
that you spend on the application spends
not garbage collection right so the more
frequent you this the collections happen
and then then you are spending time
garbage collector so it just it does
affect your throughput and that's that's
what could bring your application
effectiveness down cuz you're not able
to process as many requests so you're
not able to handle so many federal
requests or something like that yes and
eventually down the line what happens is
it adds up so while you are pausing for
garbage collection so many requests came
in but you were not able to handle so
now you have Q whatever queue you had
would have an impact and then so you
know it's like a deferred because now
you have to handle more requests and
again all these things so the queue gets
impacted because of your cause if I have
application where I want very uniform
predictable latency without outliers I
might be looking at bringing on more
servers that are gonna operate at each
one at a lower throughput or maybe
rotating servers on and off line so I
can do the more disruptive garbage
collections when the server is
temporarily detached and then bring it
back online
yeah people and people people do that
people it's crazy and and important that
how people have learned to live with
with what they had so they have
non-genetic will see a math lecture they
have lunch in it with the serial marks
we compact from did full GC failsafe GC
so that's exactly what B
will do and and and it makes sense in
many places I I know G 1 G C is not
there yet with what predictable times
are concerned but most of them than not
if you have little flexibility in your
worst case response time and then G 1 G
C can be tuned such that you do not
encounter an evacuation failure or a
promotion failure which was Mitchie once
you see as you would have had with what
CMS you know the fragmentation issue if
you tuned in Jakarta first like their
appropriately and if you give it enough
heat and you have not strict like not 10
milliseconds fast time requirement or
something g1 GC can actually be tuned I
in most cases to to avoid that full
compacting single-threaded Marc Marc and
sweet confection you know so yes I mean
people just have to I guess in a way
learn more about this new collector and
and one of the things that I'm doing
actually is I'm giving talks about
garbage first luggage collection because
in open JDK and 9 Java 9 the one of the
things is that g1 first
garbage garbage collector is going to be
the default collector up until now the
prattle GC collected the super collector
was the default for vector but John Lyon
will bring about G 1 GC as a default
collector so so there's a lot of
Education that needs to be done and
people need to try and and try this to
Eunji's and collection and bring their
observations to the table talk about it
you know open JDK forums so that there's
more observation when they did to how to
make garbage collector better if I get
to the point where I'm gonna take a
server offline because I want to avoid
visible garbage collection behavior then
to me that sounds like I've almost given
up and before I would do that I hope I
could tune the JVM what are some of the
things that customers or users want the
JVM
to do and how do they express that to
you so most often they're not again JPM
and Jessie I'm kind of when somebody
comes what comes to me they they talk
about the problem areas more are most
often than not it's it's got to do with
the tuning that you mentioned and and at
that particular point they're not even
concerned about the worst case because
they already know there are some
low-hanging optimizations that can be
done and so they think that they haven't
even achieved a proper scalable run a
scalable set of options where they can
go ahead and talk about the absolute
worst case so so simple things where for
example references of our big thing so
turning on parallel reference processing
that helps them a lot sometimes just
sizing the generations a little bit or
trying to find out their live data set I
mentioned that briefly trying to find
out the live data set is this is a big
thing sometimes people are not aware
about
compressed hoops on heaps as much as 64
I guess now with JDK 8 so if you do the
alignment if you change the alignment to
16 bytes you can achieve compress terms
it's not the same as when with 8 but
yeah 8 bytes it's but it's still you're
still getting compressed routes up to 64
gigs of heat so there's some kind of
education that needs because of this so
Java is the JVM is getting better right
and every time we move to a different
verb that came out from 6 to 7 to 8
there are so many different things that
education is the key people need to be
aware of for so many other optimizations
within within the JVM itself there's the
the Numa people are using that now but
there was a whole education of using the
numa numa where allocator so things like
that are just low-hanging fruits that
that people I mean not everybody that I
would work with me to there some of them
they're very savvy and they already know
what they need and it's just a matter of
looking at the application profiling it
and and figuring out what's going on
what's causing these increasing
references issue or what's causing some
kind of scalability bottleneck and and
sometimes profiling the heap itself
sometimes threat profiling that
sometimes the application for funding
are the way to go but yes there are lots
of options that people can people can
learn about with respect to their dingy
bein what are some tools that
performance engineers use to understand
how their garbage collection is working
and pinpoint areas for improvement one
of the things that I tell all my clients
is that there are two options that
everybody should enable in production
and that's one of them is xx friend GC
details and then then the other one is
when GC time stands for date stamps with
with those what and then 3 director of
GC log and and you do the augmentation
or whatever you need to
but with that with those enabled I can
see basically how your generations like
are getting filled the the allocation
rate the promotion rate I can I can see
those simple things and we can talk
about that just by looking at your GC
log I can look at your heap occupancy
how how the occupancy you know not just
your heap size how it goes but how the
origin occupancy changes while the young
Janaka finsihed changes and all those
things aren't easily visible just by
doing the PCC details
did you see data items ok so when you
turn on these GC details
you get output out to a log file that it
gives you a lot of information about
what's going
on during garbage collection and then
you could maybe parse that and feed that
into some kind of statistical or
analytical software and average it over
time things like that well what I I
don't look at average is what I look at
is actual almost actual GC so I don't
plant all these actual juices there's
something called GC histo so I'll parse
this log file and provide the
information that GC histo needs and then
GC histo is basically a histogram and it
it provides you information it can
actually visualize these individual
events and then you can see how much
time each each of those events took and
then I can if I see that oh one of these
collections is going past say 500
milliseconds so I'm gonna go investigate
that further and then that's how we
start but if I don't even have that much
visibility into the GC then I don't get
the starting point so so definitely
enable when GC details and when GC dates
time j-dub time stands and and look at
the lawns I see so it's more like
debugging or you're looking at
individual cases rather than aggregated
behavior and try and understand what
happened in each individual case yeah by
the time somebody comes to me they have
a problem so we know that they are
looking for for our detailed analysis
and and so at that time looking at
averages is not going to help me at all
maybe looking at 99 the five nines or
whatever yes that will help me maybe
looking at the worst case of course
that's gonna help me so so now that I've
figured out what the worst case I still
need to figure out what events led up to
that worst case right so so that's why I
need to look at the entire the entire
set of events to identify what what
happened so it's kind of a pattern on
looking for patterns in the log and and
I'm trying to plot the same info
nation in different ways I look at the
occupants and so what happens here why
did the promotion rate go up or why or
what happened here so I can go back to
the people and ask them hey I see this
allocation pattern changes and I think
that's because of that is something with
the promotion rate that changed or
whatever you know I can talk about these
different things if I can visualize what
happened to the garbage collector so
this new crane so sure and then you need
to find one of the many parameters that
affect garbage collection that you think
will impact the cause of the issue and
try setting that to a different value
that is correct we do this experiment
that is correct so very simply when I do
get a lot most of them they're not they
may have some things that and some
options in there that are not necessary
or sometimes they're kind of tightening
the flexibility that the garbage
collector needs so I start with
something or I try to get a baseline
first so by simply looking at the first
log I can say hey remove that option if
you can and this one and that one and
that one and just kind of clean up you
can bang on option and then ask for a
baseline sometimes the baseline may have
a little more than just the maximum heat
and passed on goal for example in g1
Juicy's case and they even have the
marking threshold and adjusted but that
would be the baseline after the baseline
is established then we go ahead and try
improve set of options which that for
that I may ask for more for example
there's something called trend adaptive
size policy which tells me when you
enable that it tells me exactly what you
want to see how it made up its
collection said you know how many
regions were in each collection set and
gives me all these the other details
like why did this next collection start
what and with these ink sets and what's
the percentage how much of how much each
collection was able to retrieve
anemometers in space so all that in
venturing on adding these kind of
diagnostic options so I can
figure out exactly what is wrong and how
we can make it better I see do you
combine your knowledge of how each
garbage collector works and what that
garbage collector is trying to do to
interact with the system to drive your
choice of which Diagnostics are going to
give you the most information yeah that
will drive a hypothesis of what what it
is you could change to improve the
performance in the way you want it to go
yes that's right and and and more often
than not experience matters right I
fight when I look at a log and when
somebody else looks at that log you know
I can I can see a pattern and I'm
thinking okay that's that's something
that I need to investigate you know and
if I show the same lock to somebody else
they may or may not be able to see the
pattern or they may find something else
altogether which is awesome as well so
you know it's it's all about it's it's a
fun game fun interactive game and keeps
me very interested all the time because
I learned so much from it all the time
as well and now I kind of have every
time I see a pattern I'd say okay this
is what it is let's do this and then
then after that is Szczecin let's try
this option then so at any given time I
if I'm tuning I'm only on adding one
option at a time because that way I can
see and they can and and of course they
can also see the impact of that option
so that way I can explain to them first
why I think that the option is important
and then second ones to see the impact
they can also validate what I was saying
and it kind of helps them understand
going forward their application behavior
and how the GC needs to cope up with it
or whatever right right well very
scientific in your approach I've also
heard some developers say that server
technologies that need predictable
latency should not be written in a
garbage collection language and you are
seeing some servers written in C and C++
there they may believe that's impossible
to tune or that is the difficulty of
tuning is so great that they
want something that can be more under
their control what what is your view on
that called debate what for me it
depends on the past angle they're trying
to achieve people that are trying to get
microseconds or milliseconds for sure
but like less than you know so in that
range yes everything you know you have
specialized like FPGAs and stuff like
that two people are doing that
co-locating like when you're doing the
trading you want to communicate as close
not happen network cable run all the all
the way you know where speed of light
matter matters in those cases yes I mean
Java is a lot of competition right
because Java is what a Java it's it's
abstraction right so when they want to
get to a particular field directly and
they want to make changes directly
allocation they want to be in charge of
everything that they're allocating and
so yeah I mean it does it doesn't make
sense in that in that very very low
latency arena you know when we talk
about servers I don't think most of the
servers need that much of specific low
latency requirement they don't have that
kind of it because network is is the
most dominating latency factory right so
if somebody tells me that I have servers
one one in this entry gene and one in
the other region and I'm trying to
optimize garbage collector and then I
would like to have data from both of
them and try to figure out the garbage
collection it's in fact a problem
sometimes people blame garbage collector
for everything
right but then I try to look at their
application logs I try to look at the
garbage collecting one I tried to put it
all together and try to tell them that
see your own garbage collector was at
any given time not over 500 millisecond
then indexed
over 500 milliseconds pause but your
application is having this kind of issue
so maybe we should investigate something
else right safe points are another
reason you know it doesn't have to be
safe points and it's not the world
doesn't have to be just garbage
collector there are the reasons why that
could have happened so we go and
investigate something else as well
garbage collector may not always be the
issue I've also seen some talks like
Martin Thompson and the L Mack system
where they adopt programming techniques
to stay off the heap like allocating big
chunks of memory and creatively reusing
them in ways that were probably not
thought of by the developers of the Java
language do you think some kind of mix
of specialized programming techniques
and garbage collection is a pragmatic
solution to the needs of very high
performance applications yes Martin
thumps and Peter Marie on and yeah a
couple of other people that I know are
totally doing exactly what you said and
it makes sense because again the realm
that they are in there the goal that
they're trying to achieve it you know
they're trying to reduce allocations
they're trying to again couldn't the
whole thing about garbage collection is
not just the collection and stuff is
also the allocation sometimes people and
allocation and the expense those
allocations come with you know so I
think what they're doing is what makes
perfect sense for for the field that
they're dealing with and yes but bottom
line is yes it does make sense I'm aware
that in a upcoming version of Java there
will be support for staying off the heap
for programmers that want to avoid
garbage question explain how that's
going to work so in Java 10 actually
Java 1 this year the keynote one of the
keynote speakers Brian mentioned about
project Panama and what it does is that
it aims at keeping JVM direct access
to the native data like the data in the
native heat and also code for example if
you had si si functions and stuff like
that so there there's a tool
I think it's called che extract and the
world the way that works is that it
extracts the meta data for example the
header files and stuff like that and it
generates its own so it does it for you
basically to mix these Java interfaces
so that way it gives you this kind of
way to work with your code and data so
it's pretty cool the way it works and
and Brian actually walked us through an
example and how he could call look at
there was a time library and also struct
which is like really a pain point rate
of Java so Brian showed us an example
how they could do that and so then
eventually end up just calling the
getters and setters for the to the
fields directly because J extract does
everything else for you so it's pretty
cool yeah it's called project minimal
great and there's a final question where
do you see Java garbage collection going
in the future would you say it's pretty
much a solved problem and a mature
technology or are there going to be more
developments and improvements in this
area oh yeah there's gonna be a lot lot
more improvements to this area I think
today as far as hotspot is concerned we
are at a good starting point you know it
sounds ridiculous coming from a person
who has worked with garbage collectors
for more than a decade saying that today
is a good starting point but what I mean
by that is that we have learned a lot we
have learned from the throughput
collector we have learned from the low
latency collector we have learned and
that's what gave us G 1 G 1 GC action
after all the learning in the education
about scalability bottlenecks and about
you know if incremental compaction how
to do it right we have learned about
that but we haven't yet mastered from
deterministic collection yet we haven't
yet math
without having super you know super
extends on throughput right so we
haven't mastered that we haven't
mastered larger heaps with g1 yes that's
a starting point but what about g1 for
throughput what about g1 from low
latency so those are the next steps so I
live in a future where the visualized
heap framework is going to be the base
framework for garbage collection and I
also see specialized effort towards
gearing garbage collectors too much low
latency predictable agency and
deterministically to the scene which
means that you can move towards you know
no stop the world process or something
like that so there are there's already
work then like us more zoom this has
worked with this and there they deal
with very large heap sciences and no
pause right so there is there's work
done and I see an open JDK hot spot
moving to to that realm I also see
throughput collection and I'm moving to
the regionalised he framework it's so
much easier when you when you're
adaptiveness is just based on adding or
subtracting a region right instead of
having pre-allocated area where we could
expand to in the future in a contiguous
heap manner so there are lots of issues
with the existing GC frameworks and I
think g1 should see screen work is going
to be the new norm and I you know of
course iBM has their balance teams I
think there's another shenandoah which
is also a regional team it's an open JDK
knows only thing and so I yeah I see
that as the future great for our
listeners you'd like to learn more about
your work or follow you where should
they go well I I write articles to in
the queue so it's infocomm and then just
my name Monica Beckwith
just tripped me up I also can follow me
on Twitter it's mom deck I'll just go
back mo n under snow deck and that way
they
reach out to me on Twitter and then I
can help them with their needs so yeah
Monica Beckwith thank you very much for
speaking to software engineering radio
well thank you for our listeners we
would love to get feedback from you you
can email us at team at SC - radio
dotnet follow us on twitter at SP radio
contact us at our group on google+
linkedin or facebook or go to itunes and
write a review for the show for software
engineering radio this has been Robert
blumen thank you for listening thanks
for listening to SC radio an educational
program brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine for more information
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website @ SC -
radioman to provide feedback you can
write comments on each episode on the
website or write a review on itunes
mention a message us on twitter at SC
radio or search for the software
engineering radio group on linkedin
Google+ or Facebook you can also email
us at team at se - radio net this and
all other episodes of SU radio is
licensed under the creative commons 2.5
license thanks again for your support
[Music]
[Applause]
you